<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Fredrik K. Gustafsson | PhD Student in Probabilistic Deep Learning</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Fredrik K. Gustafsson | PhD Student in Probabilistic Deep Learning</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; Fredrik K. Gustafsson 2023</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Explaining machine learning and how it can be used to help doctors</title>
      <link>/post/explaining_ml/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/explaining_ml/</guid>
      <description>For a project in the doctoral course Using Maths and CS to do Social Good at Uppsala University, our goal was to make grade 7-9 students more interested in mathematics. To that end, we have created a video with an accompanying interactive blog post. In the video, we explain the essence of how machine learning works and how it can be used to help doctors discover heart attacks from patient ECGs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting started with PyTorch:&lt;br&gt; 1 - Linear regression</title>
      <link>/post/19apr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/19apr/</guid>
      <description>All code found in this blog post is also available on Google Colab where it can be executed directly in the browser.
When I first got interested in deep learning a couple of years ago, I started out using TensorFlow. In early 2018 I then decided to switch to PyTorch, a decision that I&amp;rsquo;ve been very happy with ever since. Today, the difference between the two frameworks is probably quite small in practice (and both are extensively used by researchers in the field), but I personally still find PyTorch more convenient to use.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>News</title>
      <link>/post/news/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/news/</guid>
      <description>[Mar 16, 2023] Today I presented Some Advice for New (and Old?) PhD Students [slides] at our weekly division meeting.
 [Feb 8, 2023] New preprint: How Reliable is Your Regression Model&amp;rsquo;s Uncertainty Under Real-World Distribution Shifts? [arXiv] [code] [project].
 [Jan 27, 2023] New preprint: Image Restoration with Mean-Reverting Stochastic Differential Equations [arXiv] [code] [project].
 [Dec 21, 2022] New preprint: ECG-Based Electrolyte Prediction: Evaluating Regression and Probabilistic Methods [arXiv] [code] [project].</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>