<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Fredrik K. Gustafsson | Postdoc | Machine Learning for Computational Pathology</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Fredrik K. Gustafsson | Postdoc | Machine Learning for Computational Pathology</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; Fredrik K. Gustafsson 2024</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>My Year of Reading in 2023</title>
      <link>/post/year_of_reading_2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/year_of_reading_2023/</guid>
      <description>In 2023, I read 87 papers and 26 non-technical books. 87 papers is slightly more than my previous record (82 papers in 2022), and I&amp;rsquo;ve never even been remotely close to reading 26 books in a year. Deciding to read more books is definitely one of the best things I did in 2023, it&amp;rsquo;s a great way to relax and learn some new things about the world.
In 2024, I want to read at least 100 papers and 12 non-technical books.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The How and Why of Reading 300 Papers in 5 Years</title>
      <link>/post/phd_of_reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/phd_of_reading/</guid>
      <description>The header image above was generated using the text-to-image tool at imagine.art, from the input &amp;ldquo;teddy bear scientists having an intense discussion in a reading group about machine learning&amp;rdquo;.
Since I started my PhD almost five years ago (in September 2018), I have categorized, annotated and written short comments for all research papers I read in detail. I share this publicly in a GitHub repository, and recently reached 300 read papers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Explaining Machine Learning and How It Can Be Used to Help Doctors</title>
      <link>/post/explaining_ml/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/explaining_ml/</guid>
      <description>For a project in the doctoral course Using Maths and CS to do Social Good at Uppsala University, our goal was to make grade 7-9 students more interested in mathematics. To that end, we have created a video with an accompanying interactive blog post. In the video, we explain the essence of how machine learning works and how it can be used to help doctors discover heart attacks from patient ECGs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with PyTorch:&lt;br&gt; 1 - Linear Regression</title>
      <link>/post/19apr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/19apr/</guid>
      <description>All code found in this blog post is also available on Google Colab where it can be executed directly in the browser.
When I first got interested in deep learning a couple of years ago, I started out using TensorFlow. In early 2018 I then decided to switch to PyTorch, a decision that I&amp;rsquo;ve been very happy with ever since. Today, the difference between the two frameworks is probably quite small in practice (and both are extensively used by researchers in the field), but I personally still find PyTorch more convenient to use.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feedback</title>
      <link>/post/feedback/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/feedback/</guid>
      <description>Please feel free to leave any type of anonymous feedback on my presentation at the following link: https://forms.gle/pfkhxdRzEE7ETmcs8</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>News</title>
      <link>/post/news/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/news/</guid>
      <description>[Jan 29, 2024] New blog post: My Year of Reading in 2023.
 [Jan 16, 2024] Accepted paper: Controlling Vision-Language Models for Multi-Task Image Restoration, work lead by the incredibly skilled Ziwei Luo, has been accepted to ICLR 2024.
 [Dec 8, 2023] I have joined the group of Mattias Rantalainen at Karolinska Institutet as a postdoc to work on computational pathology.
 [Nov 30, 2023] I have successfully defended my PhD thesis Towards Accurate and Reliable Deep Regression Models [pdf] [DiVA] [slides] [video].</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>