<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Fredrik K. Gustafsson | PhD Student in Uncertainty-Aware Deep Learning</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Fredrik K. Gustafsson | PhD Student in Uncertainty-Aware Deep Learning</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; Fredrik K. Gustafsson 2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting started with PyTorch:&lt;br&gt; 1 - Linear regression</title>
      <link>/post/19apr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/19apr/</guid>
      <description>All code found in this blog post is also available on Google Colab where it can be executed directly in the browser.
When I first got interested in deep learning a couple of years ago, I started out using TensorFlow. In early 2018 I then decided to switch to PyTorch, a decision that I&amp;rsquo;ve been very happy with ever since. Today, the difference between the two frameworks is probably quite small in practice (and both are extensively used by researchers in the field), but I personally still find PyTorch more convenient to use.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>News</title>
      <link>/post/news/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/news/</guid>
      <description>[Oct 1, 2019] Accepted workshop paper: Evaluating Scalable Bayesian Deep Learning Methods for Robust Computer Vision has been accepted to the workshop on Bayesian Deep Learning at NeurIPS 2019.
 [Sep 27, 2019] New preprint: DCTD: Deep Conditional Target Densities for Accurate Regression [arXiv] [slides] [project].
 [Jun 5, 2019] New preprint: Evaluating Scalable Bayesian Deep Learning Methods for Robust Computer Vision [arXiv] [code] [video] [project].
 [May 18, 2019] I will present our extended abstract on ensembling as approximate Bayesian inference at SSDL19, June 10 [slides].</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>